Penmanship Collection
Penmanship Collection
1881-1955
1 linear ft.
Correspondence, printed material and specimens of late 19th and early 20th century penmanship; much of the correspondence is address to L.A. Platz, an "expert penman" living in Syracuse, New York. Includes correspondence with noted penman Albert Meub as well as the Zaner-Bloser Company and its Zanerian College of Penmanship.
4597240
Biographical History
According to The Educator, "L. A. Platz, Hand-Writing Expert, Syracuse, N. Y... is a very skillful penman and was a very close friend of the late A. W. Dacon [Dakin]." [Vol. 48, No. 5, January 1943].
Albert P. Meub of Pasadena, California was "a penman of national note," known for his efforts to retain penmanship as part of the regular school curriculum, and an inductee into the Penman's Hall of Fame. In a 1927 letter to Platz (not part of this collection), he writes, "I, too, believe you should take up the teaching work. You are such a fine penman I know that you would have big success."
The Zanerian College of Penmanship was founded by Master Penman Charles Paxton Zaner in 1888. In 1895, after noted penman Elmer Ward joined the firm, it became known as the Zaner-Bloser Company. Its script was a streamlined version of Spencerian. It offered penmanship courses and published professional materials about handwriting and illustration. The company still exists today.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Penmanship Collection contains correspondence, printed material and specimens of fine penmanship.
Correspondence, L. A. Platz contains letters to expert penman L. A. Platz of Syracuse, New York. Correspondents include other notable penmen such as Henry Behrensmeyer, A. W. Dakin, Melvin H. Leib, Albert Meub, Charles Romont, and Francis L. Tower. Many are beautifully written and some are ornamented. There are also numerous letters from aspiring penmen, with samples of their work, and some general correspondence.
Printed material contains two publications from the Zanerian College of Penmanship, and assorted advertisements and circulars relating to penmanship and writing supplies.
Specimens contains autograph albums, business cards (handwritten), and scrapbooks. The scrapbooks include examples of Spencerian, copperplate, engrossing (a large, round, legible hand), and other similar scripts, as well as some examples of ornamentation such as the classic "bird flourish." There are also numerous examples of white ink on colored paper.
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetical by name or topic.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Illustrators; New York State; Behrensmeyer, Henry P., 1868-1948.; Dakin, A. W.; Leib, Melvin.; Meub, Albert P.; Romont, Charles.; Zaner-Bloser (Firm); Calligraphers -- United States.; Calligraphy -- Specimens.; Calligraphy -- United States -- History.; Lettering -- Specimens.; Penmanship, American -- History.; Penmanship, American -- Specimens.; Syracuse (N.Y.); Business cards.; Correspondence.; Scrapbooks.; Specimens.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 2015.
Notebook in English and German, transfer from Rare Books, 2017.
Inventory
- Correspondence, L.A. Platz
  - Behrensmeyer, H. P., 1940 (Box 1)
  - Dakin, A. W., 1916; 1922,; 1929,; 1931-1932,; 1935-1936,; undated (Box 1)
  - Enriquez, E. C., 1941 (Box 1)
  - Hausam, L. H., 1940 (Box 1)
  - Lehman, H. B., 1916; 1926; includes specimen of bird flourish, multicolor with metallic accents (Box 1)
  - Leib, Melvin, 1941; 1952 (Box 1)
  - Meub, Albert P., 1921-1922; 1924,; 1926,; 1929,; 1933,; 1935,; 1939-1942,; 1955; includes specimen of Platz's name done with illuminated capitals and ornamentation (Box 1)
  - Morgan, W. H., 1927; 1930-1931 (Box 1)
  - Romont, Charles, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Tower, Francis L., 1927; 1940,; undated; includes hand-drawn chart of the hand, extensively annotated, with several pages of description and discussion; also a long letter describing Tower's health and how he originally planned to go into "the chicken business" (Box 1)
  - Westrope, P. A., 1933; numerous specimens, including a bird flourish, noted as done by Westrope at age 75 (Box 1)
  - Zaner-Bloser Co., 1940-1941; business advice, from E. A. Luper (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, A-Z, includes two letters from Japanese penmen, one in Hawaii and one in Tokyo (Box 1)
- Printed material
  - Zanerian publications, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, advertising circulars, paper samples, etc. (Box 1)
- Specimens
  - Autograph albums, 1881-1892; 6 volumes (Box 1)
  - Business cards, handwritten samples, some in white ink on colored paper, some ornamented (Oversize 1)
  - Practice book, 1830-1831; Louisa Kuehne; filled with words, sentences, and few copied poems; English and German (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook (I), white ink on colored paper (Oversize 1)
  - Scrapbook (II), white ink on colored paper (Oversize 1)
  - Scrapbook (III), numerous different examples (Oversize 2)
  - Miscellaneous, one unidentified volume containing hand-copied poems, extracts, etc., and some loose sheets; 2 folders (Box 1)